Guide to the William Henry Glasson Papers, 1891 - 1946 and undated UA.29.02.0033
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
William Henry Glasson papers
1891 - 1946 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Glasson, William Henry, 1874-1946
UA.29.02.0033
5.0 Linear Feet
William Henry Glasson (1874-1946) was Professor of Political Economy and Social Science at Trinity College and Duke University from 1902-1940, and Dean of the Graduate School of Arts and Sciences from 1926-1938. Glasson was instrumental in the growth of the Department of Economics and the Graduate School. Glasson specialized in U.S. pension systems. He was secretary of the Phi Beta Kappa Society for the South Atlantic district; editor of the South Atlantic Quarterly; and a member of the Durham Board of Education. Collection includes personal and professional correspondence, manuscripts, research notes, scrapbooks, diaries, account books, postcards, and photographs pertaining to Glasson's family, career, and interests. Major subjects found in the collection are the growth of the Department of Economics and the Graduate School, Trinity's efforts to obtain a Phi Beta Kappa chapter, and Duke University's contract with the Teachers Insurance and Annuity Association of America. English.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The William Henry Glasson Papers was received by the University Archives as a gift in 1954 (A48-1942) and in 1955 (A48-2022).
Biographical Note
William Henry Glasson was born in Troy, NY. on July 26, 1874. He received his Ph.B. from Cornell University in 1896 and his Ph.D. from Columbia University in 1900. Glasson was head of the Dept. of History and Civics at the George School (Newton, Pa.) from 1899-1902. He came to Trinity College in 1902. During this tenure at Trinity and Duke University, Glasson was instrumental in the development of the Dept. of Economics and the Graduate School. He was Professor of Political Economy and Social Science from 1902-1940; appointed in charge of the establishment of the retirement annuity plan for the faculty and administration; the head of the department of economics and business administration; chairman of the faculty committee on graduate instruction; and Dean of the Graduate School of Arts and Sciences from 1926-1938. Glasson was secretary of the Phi Beta Kappa Society for the South Atlantic district; editor of the South Atlantic Quarterly from 1905-1909; and a member of the Durham Board of Education.
Collection Overview
Collection includes personal and professional correspondence, manuscripts, research notes, scrapbooks, diaries, diplomas, baptismal certificate, account books, postcards, and photographs pertaining to Glasson's family, career, and interests. Major subjects found in the collection are the growth of the Department of Economics and the Graduate School, Trinity's efforts to obtain a Phi Beta Kappa chapter, and Duke University's contract with the Teachers Insurance and Annuity Association of America. Correspondence includes a letter to William P. Few (February 22, 1934) signed by 24 faculty members praising Duke's record on academic freedom, reports directed to University administrators, and copies of family genealogical material. A significant correspondent is H. Clay Evans, the U.S. Commissioner of Pensions. In 1934, Glasson and Dean Wannamaker were among a group of academics who travelled to Germany on a Carl Schurz Tour to see the effects of Hitler's rise to power. The scrapbooks include maps, clippings, postcards, notes, and an itinerary from this trip. Glasson's manuscripts include recollections of Trinity and Duke, a variety of writings and lectures on money and banking, pension systems, and Durham's charter of incorporation. There are 10 diaries (1898-1944), 3 family account books (1900-1937) including one that details Glasson's daughters' expenses while students at Duke, and scrapbooks of clippings, photographs of Glasson as a young man, poems, and photographs of Cornell University.
Related Material
Carlos Sforza Papers, 1933-1941.
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Department of Economics Records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Graduate School Records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Phi Beta Kappa, Beta of North Carolina Chapter, Records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Portrait of William Henry Glasson.
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Bibliography
Boyd, William Kenneth. The Installation of the Beta Chapter of North Carolina at Trinity College. In The Phi Beta Kappa Key: The Official Publication of the United Chapters of Phi Beta Kappa. Vol. 4, no. 4, p. 211-226. Somerville, N.J: Unionist-Gazette Association, 1920
Glasson, William Henry. History of Military Pension Legislation in the United States., New York: Columbia University Press, 1900
Scrapbooks; Diaries; Economics -- History; Academic freedom; Universities and colleges -- Faculty -- Retirement -- United States; Pensions -- United States; Germany -- Description and travel; Photographs; Diplomas; Wannamaker, William Hane, 1873-; Teachers Insurance and Annuity Association; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.); Glasson, William Henry, 1874-1946; Phi Beta Kappa. North Carolina Beta (Trinity College); Evans, Henry Clay, 1843-1921; Duke University -- History; Duke University. Graduate School; Duke University -- Faculty
- Correspondence 1891-1945
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence centers around Glasson's involvement in the Dept. of Economics and the Graduate School at Trinity College and Duke University, and his interest in pension systems. Correspondence includes a letter to William P. Few (February 22, 1934) signed by 24 faculty members praising Duke's record on academic freedom, reports directed to University administrators, and copies of family genealogical material. A significant correspondent is H. Clay Evans, the U.S. Commissioner of Pensions.
  - 1891-1906 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1907-1912 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1913-1915 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1916-1919 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1920-1925 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1926-1936 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1937-1945 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Writings 1893-1946
  Writings include class notebooks kept while Glasson was a student, manuscripts, lecture notes, diaries, account books, and personal reflections captured in poems and prose. Included are recollections of Trinity and Duke, a variety of writings and lectures on money and banking, pension systems, and Durham's charter of incorporation. There are 10 diaries (1898-1944), 3 family account books (1900-1937) including one that details Glasson's daughters' expenses while students at Duke, copies of poems, and letters to the editor written to local newspapers.
  - Class Notebooks, 1893-1897
    - Notes on lectures on economics taken at Cornell University, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Notes on the lectures given by Professor Cheyney on English economic and social history, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Notes on the lectures given by Professor Edwin R. A. Seligman on the science of finance and the history of political economy, 1899-1900 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Publication: The South's Care for Her Veterans, The American Review of Reviews, July, 1907 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Manuscripts [1914]-[1938] and undated
    - "Commission Government in American Cities," [1914] (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "Price Inflation: Its Beneficiaries and Its Victims," [1919] (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - "The Graduate School of Arts and Sciences," [1927] (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - "The Average Man's Savings," 1930 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - "The Modern University and Its Functions," Dec. 11, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - "Civil War Pensions: A Retrospective," Jan. 1, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - "Memoirs of Duke University and Trinity College," 1938. (Box 2, Folder 18)
      Includes correspondence.
    - "History of the Department of Economics and business Administration," ca. 1938 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - "Economic Effects of the World War," undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - "The European War's Economic Effects Upon the U.S.," undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - "Military Pensions and Soldiers' Insurance in the U.S.," undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - "Optional City Charter and Municipal Finance Laws in N.C.," undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - "Recent Progress in Municipal Government," undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - "The South's Pension and Relief Provisions for the Soldiers of the Confederacy," undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - "William Preston Few," undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Lecture Notes, 1938-1940 and undated
    - Lecture notes for Economics 203, [Money and Banking], 1938-1940. (Box 2, Folder 27-29)
    - "Military Pensions in American Public Finance and Politics," undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
      Five lectures delivered at Johns Hopkins University.
    - Notes and research materials, undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Diaries 1898-1944
    - 1898 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - 1900-1902 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - 1935 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - 1936 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - 1937 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - 1938 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - 1939 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - 1940 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - 1941 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - 1942 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - 1944 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Account Books 1900-1937
    - Accounts kept at the George School, Bucks County, Pa., 1900-1901 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Record book of stocks owned by William H. Glasson and Mary P. Glasson, 1907-1945 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - College expenses for Lucy P. Glasson and Mary E. Glasson, 1922-1933 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Poems and Prose [1914]-1945 and undated
    - Small book of poems and prose, 1944-1945 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Six poems, undated (Box 5, Folder 47)
- Subject Files, 1911-1938 and undated
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1911-1929 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Trinity College finances, [1912]-1920 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Pensions, 1916-1935 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Teachers Insurance and Annuity Association of America, 1918-1925 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Minutes of the meeting of the Commission on University Organization, Jan. 26, 1925 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Graduate School of Arts and Sciences, 1925-1938 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Carl Shurz tour of American professors and students to Germany, July-Aug.1934 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - South Atlantic Quarterly, undated (Box 5, Folder 55)
- Graphics, 1900-[1934] and undated
  - Photographs of family and friends, undated (Box 6, Folder 56-57)
  - Travel photographs taken in Florida, Colorado, and Venezuela and Italy, undated (Box 6, Folder 58)
  - Photographs of Cornell University and Ithaca, NY, [ca.1900] (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - [Postcards collected on Carl Schurz tour in Germany], [1934] (Box 6, Folder 60)
  - Still life, 1900 (Box 6, Folder 61)
- Clippings, 1897-1946
  - 1897-1946 (Box 6, Folder 62)
  - 1899-1946 (Box 6, Folder 63)
  - Trinity and Duke, 1920-1939 (Box 6, Folder 64)
- Souvenirs, 1897-1929
  - Programs, placecards, and invitations, 1892-1929 (Box 6, Folder 65)
  - Trinity College, 1903-1926. (Box 6, Folder 66)
    Includes commencement and graduation exercises, and a copy of Alexander Hamilton's Report on Manufactures presented to Dr. Glasson by John Franklin Crowell.
- Oversize Materials
  Included are drafts and copies of the city of Durham's charter and act to incorporate, Glasson's diplomas, and scrapbooks kept while Glasson was on the 1934 Carl Schurz Tour to see the effects of Hitler's rise to power. The scrapbooks include maps, clippings, postcards, notes, and an itinerary from this trip.
  - Proposed charter and act to incorporate the city of Durham, 1915-1921 (Box 6, Oversize-folder 7, Folder 67)
  - Scrapbooks
    - 1896-1939 (Box 6, Folder 68)
    - [ca.1900]-1941 (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - Diplomas and Baptismal certificate, 1874-1939 (Oversize-folder 1, Oversize-folder 2)